Hello, and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan, and what we are doing today
is finding the empirical and molecular
formula from percent compositions.
Uh, now, if you are not familiar
with the mass percent composition,
please refer to my previous video on
that, so that way you can make sure
you understand how to use percents.
Now, before we get into it, though, really
is, let's try to go into really what is
the difference between these two things.
Because, honestly, whenever I saw
these as a general chemistry student,
it was extremely overwhelming and
extremely confusing to try to be able
to figure out what the difference is
between these two general definitions.
So let's take a look at it, try
to decipher it, so that way you're
able to understand it and to
solve these in your introductory
or your general chemistry course.
Okay,
so the whole idea with this
is really, well, what is it?
Well, the first thing is that word
empirical formula, which is the simplest
whole number ratio of every atom that's
found within a molecular formula.
And when you read that, you're like, what?
There's so much, so many science
terms that are being used.
Let's try to break it down.
So the first thing is, let's say if
I have the following species here.
So I have a butane here.
So the same thing that
you have in lighters.
And what we're going to do is we're
going to count how many elements
there are with inside the species.
Meaning we're going to count the
number of carbons and the number of
hydrogens that are all around it.
So the first thing you gotta do is you
gotta identify what each element is.
So we see we have a C
and then we have an H.
Now what we're gonna do is we're going
to count all these little pieces.
'cause what the molecular formula
represents is what the actual
composition is of this molecule.
So this is the, the, uh, reg, well,
let's call it the regular formula.
So it's what you're going to
see in a chemical reaction.
What's actually gonna be
doing the science here.
So when we are looking at that,
what we're going to do is count all
these little orange carbons here,
and we can see we have four of them.
So we have 1, 2, 3, 4,
so it's going to be C4.
Now what we're going to do is we're
going to count all the hydrogens that
are around this, and we can see we
have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.
And let's put some numbers around them
just so that way we can see where are
all those numbers coming from, right?
So we have all these little hydrogens.
So it's going to be C4H10.
Now with the definition of empirical
formula that I mentioned before, this
is the smallest, the simplest whole
number ratio of every atom, meaning
what can we divide all those numbers
by, the C4H10, to get a simpler ratio.
So what are those values?
Well, if we can kind of think
of it, we have four and 10.
So what can you divide both
those numbers to simplify it?
Well, generally, the numbers that you
want to think of are things like 2, 3,
4, 5, those small numbers that usually
you divide things by to simplify.
So let's pick the first one, which is 2.
So if I divide both these numbers
by 2, what are you going to get?
Well, you're going to get 2, and then
you're going to get 5 for the other one.
Now, could you divide
it by another number?
Well, if you kind of think about it, well,
3 and 4 are not divisible, because this
has to be the smallest whole number ratio.
So by dividing these by 2, what we end
up getting is C2H5, which this is the
empirical formula for this compound.
Now the reason for why empirical
formulas are so important
is, has for multiple reasons.
One of them has to do with
ionic compounds, which we
only find in formula units.
When you are trying to figure out
exactly how does charges try to
cancel out and how do they exist?
The other way is well when you're
in the lab The only thing you can
do is measure a sample which is a
specific percentage of each individual
element So you got to be able to
decipher what all those things means.
Okay, so this is the idea
Let's try another one.
H, N, and O, which all have
their own different colors.
So let's first count all the carbons,
which are the ones in orange and yellow.
So when we do that, we can see that,
okay, well we have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7,
8, 9, right, all around our compound.
Now we're going to count all the
hydrogens that we have, and we can
see that, well, we have a lot of them.
So we have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, and 12.
Okay, so we have C10H12 so far.
Oh, that's a lot of numbers.
Luckily, we only have two blue ones,
which are two nitrogens, and we only
have one hydrogen, or sorry, not one
hydrogen, one oxygen within this molecule.
Now what we're going to do is, can,
are, is, are these different values, are
they divisible by a simple whole number?
So what did we have?
We had 10, Well,
one thing you're going to notice
is, oh wait, we have a 1 here.
Can we divide that by two?
Well, you can't have a
half of an element, right?
So what this tells us is that the
molecular formula and the empirical
formula are the same thing.
So it does not always have to be
something completely different.
They can be the exact same value.
Okay.
So it's always about what's the
simplest whole number ratio.
So keep that in mind.
They don't always have to
be something different.
It could be a trick question sometimes.
Right?
We love to throw, us professors love to
throw trick questions at our students.
Let's try to look at how we can actually
utilize this in a mathematical way.
Right?
So the most common way that you're
going to be seeing empirical formulas
is always through mathematics.
Chemistry is secretly a
math class in disguise.
Your professors will never admit it to
you, but it is, it's a big math class.
So let's look at, take a look at this
so that way we can understand and
interpret data, which you would, could
potentially get in the laboratory setting.
So caffeine has the following
mass percent composition, right?
Caffeine is what keeps us
all going every single day.
Um, what is the empirical formula?
And if the molar mass is 194.
19 grams per mole, what
is the molecular formula?
Oh boy.
So from these types of problems,
commonly you will get a set of
percents, which tell you how much
of each individual element exists.
Let's go through this type of problem
step by step so that way you can break
it down for any homework question or
for any type of exam style problem.
Let's take a look at it.
Alright, the first step, the how to
guide, how to solve for an empirical
formula problem, because I can
guarantee you will probably see one
on your first exam or your second
exam in a general chemistry course.
So the first thing you need to do is
assume that you have a 100 gram sample,
which allows you to convert The, the
percents into actual usable numbers.
So we need to convert the
percents for step one, and this
is actually a very easy step.
Uh, so that's the good news.
So what you're going to do
is if you look at carbon, for
example, it says we have 49.
98%.
So if we assume that this is out of
100 grams, we can simply just write 49.
98 grams of our sample
is carbon here, right?
So we can just write that assumption down.
Now for the next one, we can
do the same thing for hydrogen.
We can say we have 5.
19 grams of hydrogen We can say
that we have nine, nitrogen is 28.
85 grams of nitrogen and then
oxygen, we can say that we have 16.
48 grams of oxygen.
And when you add up all these values
together, it's, it's essentially
telling you like, Oh, within this whole
caffeine sample, we have this amount
of each element here that exists.
Now what exactly are we
going to do with that?
Well, in step two, we're
going to take these values.
And we're going to convert
them to moles, okay?
So the goal is always the mole
when it comes to chemistry.
You need to try to
convert things to moles.
So the goal is the mole.
So what we're going to do is we're going
to take each of those values that we
had above and convert them to moles.
So the very first one was at 49.
98 grams of carbon all the way at the top.
So we will take 49.
98 grams of carbon and convert
it using our molar masses.
So we have them already available
right here on the screen,
uh, from the Pirog table.
And we are going to convert them
using a little step conversion
that we've, that we've used
before in our mole videos, right?
So we cancel out our units
using that molar mass.
And what we are going to end up
getting for our first one is 4.
16 moles of carbon.
Now we're going to do this
for each individual species.
So let's do the next
one, which was hydrogen.
And what we had for that value was 5.
19 grams.
Let's put that down here at the bottom.
Let's just copy them all down.
So nitrogen was 28.
85 grams.
And then oxygen was 16.
16.
48.
Okay, when we go through this
conversion, so we'll set up our
little t tables for ourselves.
We have the 1.
008 grams for every one mole of hydrogen,
and what we are going to end up getting
when we do this conversion is 5.
15 moles of hydrogen.
For the next one, we are taking that 28.
85 grams of nitrogen, converting
that as well, using our periodic
table values, right, which was 14.
01 grams of nitrogen, and that is going
to be equivalent to one mole of nitrogen.
When we get that value,
we are going to have 2.
05 moles of nitrogen, and then we'll once
again convert the last value to moles.
Which is 15.
99 grams of oxygen for
every one mole of oxygen.
And that's going to be equivalent to 1.
03 moles of oxygen.
Now, why did we convert all of these
different values that are here?
We have so many of them available.
Now, if you can think back to what does
it mean when you're counting subscripts?
Well, a subscript represents the number
of moles within a chemical species.
However, all of these have decimals,
so how do you simplify them to
the lowest whole number ratio?
What the next step is going to be, is
you're going to divide each mole value
by the lowest number that we calculated.
Because these have to
be whole number values.
So, let's recopy these for ourselves so
we can see which one is the lowest value.
So we have carbon, we have
hydrogen, We have nitrogen.
We have oxygen.
So let's put all these down.
We have 1.
05, 2.
05, 5.
15, and 4.
16.
Now, with all those values, which
one of these is the smallest?
Well, you can quickly see
oxygen is your tiniest value.
So what we're going to do is we're going
to divide all of these values by 1.
03.
Now when you do this, it's going to lead
to a whole number value which represents
the subscript of your empirical formula.
So when we do this for oxygen,
you're going to have 1.
For nitrogen, you're going to have 2.
For hydrogen, it's going to be 5.
And for carbon, you're gonna have four.
So when you take these values,
your empirical formula is gonna
be C four, H five, and two O.
And that is how to calculate
your empirical formula.
Now the thing with this though, we're not
done yet, which there's, I've extended
this problem to a longer type of problem,
which is what if you need to calculate
what the molecular formula is as well.
'cause remember, this is just the
simplest whole number value, right?
So empirical,
so we have our empirical formula, which
is the simplest ratio, but it's not the
same thing as the molecular formula.
So let's go on to our next step.
So the next step, which is optional,
depends on the type of problem you have.
So what you need to do is
divide the molar mass of the
molecule by the empirical mass.
And what that allows you to do is
you find a, it gives you a ratio.
Which that ratio is what you're going
to multiply the empirical formula by so
let's calculate first So we have already
have the molecular mass that was given
to us in the problem So that's gonna get
plugged in or right here into our formula.
What is the empirical mass?
So we got to take this about
these, uh values and calculate it.
So let's do that So what we have right we
have four carbon atoms and we are going
to take multiply that by twelve point one
Add that by 5 hydrogens, times that by 1.
008, and as always, we want to make
sure we put all these in parentheses
for ourselves, plus nitrogen,
right, we have 2 nitrogens, 14.
01, plus 1 oxygen.
Now when we add up all of these
values, these are going to be in
grams per mole of your empirical
formula, which is going to be 97.
09 grams per mole of
your empirical formula.
And what we're going to do with that
value is that's going to then get plugged
in to this equation above as well.
So, let's take those two
values and divide them.
So we'll have 194.
19 grams per mole, divided by 97.
09 grams per mole.
and we will get a ratio of 2.
Now what does that tell us?
So the last step is using the ratio.
So what we need to do is take the
ratio and times that by the empirical
formula, which from before was C4H5N2O,
and by doing that, it's gonna give
you what the actual molecular formula
is, which is C8H10N4O2, which is
what keeps us going every single day.
This is the formula of caffeine,
the molecular formula, so that's
the true identity of it versus
the empirical formula, which
is the most simplified version.
I hope that this video helped you
by going through the steps and
listing them out on how to do it.
I recommend trying to practice these
kinds of problems for yourselves because I
really have never seen a general chemistry
or a introductory chemistry teacher does
not give this kind of problem on an exam.
Practice it.
I hope this helped and please hit
that like and subscribe button.
I hope to see you around
for future videos.
I'll see you all later now.
Bye now.